<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:distill="https://distill.pub/journal/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>casualR</title>
    <link>https://casualr.netlify.app/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://casualr.netlify.app/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <description>Really specifics solutions to really specifics problems I have encountered.</description>
    <generator>Distill</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title> WWI VieweR, A shiny app to visualize the battles of the first world war</title>
      <dc:creator>Etienne Rolland</dc:creator>
      <link>https://casualr.netlify.app/posts/WWI_viewer</link>
      <description>


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://casualr.netlify.app//posts/WWI_viewer/1672913731402.jpeg" alt="" /&gt;
&lt;p class="caption"&gt;wwi_viewer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h1 id="wwi-viewer"&gt;WWI VieweR&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi everyone ! Long time no see. I recently undertook to validate the
capstone project of the &lt;a
href="https://www.coursera.org/specializations/jhu-data-visualization-dashboarding-with-r"&gt;Data
Visualization specialization of the Johns Hopkins University on
Coursera&lt;/a&gt;, with something that was probably a slight overkill for the
requirements. Beeing without any idea around the 10th November, I came
up with the idea of visualizing the battles of the first world war the
11th.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The app is hosted here : &lt;a
href="https://cdk296.shinyapps.io/WWI_VieweR/"
class="uri"&gt;https://cdk296.shinyapps.io/WWI_VieweR/&lt;/a&gt; and the code of
the application and of the scrapping is accessible &lt;a
href="https://github.com/Cdk29/Capstone_project"&gt;on this github
repo.&lt;/a&gt; The structure of the repo is somewhat messy because of the
structuring of the course in different weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up carrying this project quite longer than I expected (cf the
date of this blog post). I also learnt some things that I did not
expected to learn, such as how to query Dbpedia using SPARQL with the
help of ten years old R-bloggers posts. I discovered some battles and
fronts. Also, even if you know that the war had a huge impacts on the
societies of the time, plotting the percentage of death per population
certainly help to grasp what this could have means for the
contemporaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also discovered that, when you are French and start by plotting the
battles of the western front, the current map of the world provided by
leaflet works very well, since boundaries did not changed since one
century. When you start plotting the battles of other fronts, such as
the middle east, it became quickly out-of-context. I remember that T.E.
Lawrence mentioned Mesopotamia and probably Persia in his books,
countries you will have trouble to find now on a map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="data"&gt;Data:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I originally started with the &lt;a
href="https://github.com/jrnold/CDB90"&gt;CDB90&lt;/a&gt; dataset, planning to
recover the latitude and longitude for each battle from Dbpedia. But the
URLs links inside the battles.csv where somewhat too old, and query
using them were not working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up querying directly dbpedia, using the code in the file
Week_2.Rmd and scrapping_all_ww1.Rmd (the file is named Week_2 because
of the segmentation of the capstone project course on Coursera)/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href="https://github.com/Cdk29/Capstone_project"&gt;the github
repo.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="some-data-limitation"&gt;Some Data limitation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facts in history are not that objective or simple. For exemple, is a
battle a victory or not ? Take for example the &lt;a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battle_of_Jutland"&gt;Battle of
Jutland&lt;/a&gt;, both camps claimed victory, because they were pursuing
differents objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, some results of battle may vary depending the language used for
scrapping &lt;em&gt;(for the second world war I remember that the protagonist
of the liberation of Rome is somewhat different based on the langage
consulted ;p)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding the scrapping, I am pretty sure some battles are missings,
for exemple in the eastern front of the war. Not sure why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, the map where I mapped the battles is a contemporary map. Too
bad there is not a world map of 1914 accessible on Leafleat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="r distill-force-highlighting-css"&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
      <distill:md5>333f7289a826978def36233ceb8f7680</distill:md5>
      <guid>https://casualr.netlify.app/posts/WWI_viewer</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
